hey guys in today's video i'm going to
show you a practice session with
anna and what i usually do with my
players is start with rallying
and then end with drills and this
particular session was an hour and a
half
so we did about 45 minutes of rallying
and then 45 minutes of drill so i'm not
going to show you
the rallying portion we're going to skip
right to drills
where some interesting things were
discussed and make sure you stay tuned
until the end of the video
where i explain why i made a slight
change
to anna's forehand technique
okay let's start off i'm going to give
you like some muscle memory some
repetition okay i'm going to drop feed
and i want you to hit tons of forehands
in a row just to get in the groove go
right down the baseline
good and again and finish all the way
and make sure you finish it all the way
there it is
all right now what i'm going to do is
i'm going to base i'm going to move you
around a little bit okay
and you're just going to follow my lead
and you're going to hit four hands
good make sure you stay on your toes and
keep moving your feet
come on great just follow the ball
good back it up okay
get out of the way we'll get out of the
way a little bit
good want to run all right
come on get out of the way good
let's do lateral forehand so i'm going
to push you wide okay
the difficulty when you go wide is that
you still want to rotate right you want
to go like this but when you're
sometimes when you're running this way
your momentum is carrying you in this
direction is more hard to turn your body
so when you're doing these shots make
sure that you're turning as well
you're not playing the ball sideways
yeah you go around the water bottle
every time here we go
good come around the water bottle all
the way around
and we'll do a set of ten come on again
another one around and one more
okay here's the important thing when you
do a when you do a
tennis specific movement is that when
you're in the middle of waiting the
first thing you do is you turn like this
and now you're running in this direction
okay you're running to the ball like
this
and now you're gonna hit the ball and
now the way you should go back to the
middle is with sidesteps so you sidestep
back to the middle like this
the reason for that is is that when
you're playing against someone
and let's say you hit a forehand from
here and then you turn around you're
running like this if they hit it in the
same direction you would have to turn
your body around you wouldn't have
enough time so
when you're sideways you can change
directions super fast
the only exception would be where you
would have to run to the middle would be
if you
get pulled way off the court like this
too wide
and now the other person hits it over
there you would have to run there you
won't be able to make it with side steps
so there's exceptions to the rule but
generally speaking you always want to
side step back to the middle
okay and do that now okay same thing
yeah the same thing backhand you you go
back and
you turn you hit it and then when you're
done you sidestep back to the middle
okay same thing but let's do one more
round of four hands
side step back good job this is good
movement right there nice
good timing too make sure you finish a
little bit longer
okay now i'm gonna make you practice
going backwards on the forehand okay
so you're gonna stand i'm gonna put the
this a little bit more in front
you're standing right here in front of
the bottom
and now you're going to practice going
backwards and hitting a forehand which
happens all the time when you play you
know it happens
very frequently someone for example
gives you a high ball and you have to
back up
and what's important on the deep ball is
that you're not too sideways like this
because now you'll have a very difficult
time rotating because
you're moving backwards so you're just
going to fall like this and you probably
have to moonball the ball back so
try to be a little bit more open with
your feet as you set up for the
sort of depot you back up open up a
little bit and now
there's a good chance you'll be able to
rotate your body and hit a normal
forehand
all right so let's try it out you stay
in front of the water bottle
and you go back all right do it again
come around yes and back it up
and go set up good i hit it freely
come again good job nice
excellent job all right now we're gonna
do very similar but we're going forward
this time okay
now when you go forward there's a couple
different ways to go forward
you can go all the way to the service
line and do something called like a half
court shot
which is different from what we're gonna
do now this is more of a ball where the
ball is a little bit
slower has a little bit less penetration
you have to step up to it
like you won't be able to wait here to
play it you'll have to step up to it
like this so i want to set up this thing
right here you're going to go behind the
water bottle
and you're going to come up and then
you're going to go behind okay and the
ball is going to be
like halfway between the service line
and the baseline okay here we go
okay go around this way there you go
back around and come
yes and again a lot of people struggle
with this ball it's actually skipping
again right
yes what do you mean by skipping
yes yes please this is a tennis footwork
you need this you need this
good
interesting so there you know what you
got there early and you were able to
stop
and play it like this a little bit more
open i have no problem with that that
was a good shot
and again good another one
again okay now we combine both and we do
one deep one short
all right so we're gonna put the water
bottle right here you're gonna stand
right in the middle
and now you go deep here you go around
and then you go short here
okay like that okay we practice both now
because you know what the reality is
when you play
you seldomly are going to be able to
stay right there and play you're going
to be moved
everywhere you know forward backward to
the sides that's the reality of tennis
you know you got to move
a lot here we go deep and i come around
and i go short okay
and again
good and we go short
okay that one you didn't set properly
come deep
i like that and go short come on up
okay yeah gig yeah brace then get
comfortable on the ball don't be
like don't be uncomfortable with your
setup i want you to set up comfortably
yes if it feels awkward you probably
have the wrong setup okay
deep good go around
and short there that felt a little
uncomfortable right
do it again get comfortable on the ball
go again around come on can't get
comfortable
you're still uncomfortable get more
towards the ball look get a little
closer to that ball you're kind of like
stopping and waiting but remember the
ball has no penetration
get towards it a little bit it's gonna
feel better
good go around and i'm short
better yes i like that one nice
much better nice job i just have to like
adjust better to the ball
and remember your phrase helped a lot
when you said
you have all time in the world for the
shot
which like doesn't make sense because
the
ball is flying too so fast well
you know what it is it's a it's a thing
that happens to recreational players
where
the way they sequence the stroke they
don't really don't have time
because here's what happened like
they're playing and they're standing
like this
and now they're waiting and as soon as
they see the ball coming to them
they think about hitting it they do
everything at once in other words
they're trying to take the racket back
and they're trying to turn the body
they're trying to step they're trying to
set up
everything at once and so it all looks
like hectic so the ball comes and
they're going like
like this you know like it looks hectic
it doesn't look rhythmic
but when you see good players like high
level players they sequence the stroke
in different segments
so they're not thinking about hitting
first right they're thinking about okay
where's the ball going to go so they see
it's a forehand then they turn
yeah and now the second step is they set
up they move their feet a lot
and they're not even thinking about
hitting yet when they start thinking
about
hitting initiating the stroke is when
the ball's already passed the net
and when it's close to the bounce you
start taking the racket back so when you
do it that way it does look like you
have all the time in the world
it does look like you're relaxed rather
than being hectic and trying to hit the
ball
right away when you see it you know like
the ball comes oh okay
well you know what it is it's panic
that's the simplest word to describe it
when the ball comes
most players novice players that panic
yeah where
advanced players experience players they
don't panic they
they know they have plenty of time to do
everything
now here's the tricky part though when
you're doing the first two steps the
uh initial observation and the setup
that you have to do very fast so there
has to be a lot of intensity
so you can't be standing like this you
know you'll probably be forced
uh to do something hectic so high-level
players they
they look like they have a lot of time
but yet there's some intensity
in the setup process so this is why you
have to
force yourself to be on your toes to
move your feet to have a lot of
intensity
you cannot be flat-footed because here's
what needs to happen the first two
phases
every stroke has to be set up perfectly
and that's why we're doing all these
drills because i'm making you move to
different locations
different angles and making you move all
over the place so that then when you
play against someone else when they
start giving you a lot of
balls that are not coming to you clean
there's going to be spraying all over
the place
you'll be able to move properly but you
still have to
have the intensity to move right away as
you when you see it
see a lot of people that will wait too
long they will not react to the ball
fast enough they're just waiting
waiting they won't react and they're
like oh there's the ball and they want
to try to do everything at once
and so there's no sequencing there
remember the three part sequence
observe the ball you see it's a forehand
you make a turn now you set up
and then you hit it and when you do that
you're going to look relaxed
and you're going to look like you have
plenty of time so now let's do some
backhands okay we'll do the same thing
there's a beautiful backhand look at
this
here we go
okay deep get behind it
here we go come up you notice the deep
one is hard you got to get behind the
ball
when it comes to the deep ball here's
the golden rule you never want to allow
the ball to get behind
you because then you're done you can't
really do anything once the ball gets
ahead of you you have to keep your body
behind the ball if the ball gets
behind you like this now well then you
can only do it like this
you lose your the back end shot better
because
there's less frivolousness less angle
because i'm overextended and i feel like
yeah no you're so right that's like
biomechanically super simple the
backhand there's really nothing to it
beforehand
you know what it is on the forehead
there's all these different grips
there's different
angles of the wrist there's different
angles of the arm
and it's just so many things can go
wrong and also the rotation is
completely different
and so it's far more complex complex
compared to the back end
itself yeah of course
so while the back end is more simple it
has less power because you're using the
back of the hand that's why it's called
the backhand
forehand you have a lot more strength on
this side so you have more power here
but it's more complicated you know
good back up good
get in
good body stays behind the ball better
that's the footwork that you need
one more all right very nice very nice
let's do a lateral backhand so it's
going to be the same footwork as the
forehand go in the middle
you run to the ball and sidestep back to
the middle here we go
sidestep it's fine do it again
sidestep it's all right either way is
fine don't worry about it
if you end up behind the baseline you
can go around this way if you end up in
front of the baseline you can go around
the front
good job nice
let's do short backhands now okay
always keep moving keep flowing with the
shot keep flowing with it again
come on good job nice
okay you're working on these balls that
are like very tricky to play they're
going to be
a little bit short they're not quite at
the service line
a lot of players struggle with these
that's why you got to practice them here
we go come on
excellent job nice now we're going to
now we're going to combine these drills
we're going to do forehand and backhand
okay
so you just do one deep forehand one
deep backhand you're going to be working
on
backing up and hitting come inside no no
you go like a v you start here you go
there come back there here and then you
go there yep
now we go forward so you're going to go
this way
and you're going to be coming in
all the way back back it up here make
sure you back pedal
always want to face one thing that's
important look when you're doing all
these drills you want to make sure
they're like as realistic as possible so
let's say you hit a forehand from here
like you wouldn't go like this go back
you would watch the other side right
you hit a forehand you would watch the
other side to see what's happening and
then back up towards the middle
so that's why when after you hit the
phone you have to back pedal always
watching what's going on over there
okay so with like backhand i'm just
gonna go from
the end of the question yeah so i know
like just to do this and do this
yes this is like really easy
you just hit it it's very natural so
easy and the elbows go up
yeah it looks very clean without me even
thinking about yeah
i do think the loop is very important
which you didn't have one at all because
you go to the bottom
right but now i'm thinking i'm kind of i
want to let you go back to your old
forehand
and introduce the loop very slowly like
piece by piece
not all at once yeah so just hit the
forehead like this for now
because you have see what you do again
you when you take your racket back you
like going through here
and then here it's not optimal but that
gives you the most control when you do
the loop all of a sudden you stiffen up
and the arm stops moving and
like the forehand disappears and you
told me that this was the case
yeah when you were playing like outside
of here
in the clinic and so on yeah so i would
say like go back to the normal forehand
of course you do all the other stuff
that's super important you want to you
know
make sure you finish you go up and
across that's super important finish all
the way
make sure the body is helping the the
finish but when it comes to loop
i'm going to like introduce it very
slowly piece by piece
so like if why i'm not doing the loop
right now where do i
start in terms of the ball is coming to
me so we're not doing this anymore
so i just like okay go into ready
position go in a ready position
right there and now turn that's all you
do
and hit it from there you're already
doing that if you take a look at the
recording just like do this
yeah that's it go there yeah you're
already doing that did you did it today
i was letting you do it and it looked
fine
so your racket's going like this it's
going like this here let go don't move
i'll move your racket don't don't move
your other hand let go
so the racket's going here which in a
way it's
kind of a loop right you're starting
higher but then it goes from here
down this is your forehand so you're
going like this ready position
you're turning here okay let's go to the
left hand
and now from here you're going here see
what i wanted you to do in the beginning
when we did that modern
forehand lesson i wanted you to go here
okay and i wanted you to drop it here
which
which is not that big of a difference
but for you it didn't work at all you
i think you were too mechanical from it
for some reason it was not natural so
i still we still might end up here one
day
but for now just go like this you go
here okay
you're gonna change your grip of course
change your grip and now you're gonna be
here
and then from here just take it down
like you always have you hit like five
more you'll see what i mean
change the yeah right here and just like
go this way don't even think about it
that's no good because what happens when
you do
when you do this you completely lock
everything so you're doing the loop but
you're unfortunately locking everything
so now the racket doesn't drop properly
you're hitting the forehand like this
yeah
so don't do it i'm telling you it
doesn't work right now we have to
introduce it very slowly
okay do it again just do a normal
forehand like you always have
there you go you see how natural that is
yes do it again a couple more like that
take it back how does that feel
one more down okay that's your normal
forehand right there that last one
just do that for now okay and let me
take care of the loop slowly you won't
even notice it i'm gonna
introduce it so slowly you won't even
notice over the course of
the whole year not everything at once
no problem at all i'm gonna really now
test your cardio okay so i'm gonna go
side to side 20 times
anytime one
good and here's two come on here's three
here we go four
no 19 lifted match points
wow nice job you don't even out of
breath
a little bit are you what is going on i
need to push it harder
that wasn't hard enough we'll do one
more round this time we're gonna go a
little bit stronger
ready come and go two
three get it over the net come on lift
that ball
18 no mistakes please 19
20. and bonus round
bonus bonus come on bonus
here we go 23
come on 24 here we go 25
come 26.
that's 28 two more you're going 30 we're
going all the way
and last one all right give me one more
four and you can't finish like that up
and across please
too far away give me another one one
more
and you did it all right anna are you
out of breath now
a little bit not a lot wow you have some
endurance
very impressive very impressive and we
have to do 40 next time
or 50. okay